A dramatic move for the Baltimore
Ravens. Took an extra day to think about
it, but this was always a possibility. I
don't know that we have seen in a very
long time as attractive an opening as
the Baltimore Ravens right now.
>> Timing is never right. You can't say
that timing is perfect in anything. When
you finally get to the point that you're
pretty damn sure that you are not going
to regret the decision, then that's the
time to make the decision. The Ravens is
the best job because you have Lamar
Jackson.
>> You got an organization that already has
championship pedigree. You got an owner
in Steve Bashadi that has hardware in
the trophy case. We're going to make it
so right that we're going to have a lot
of patience. Is that fair to say? We're
going to be so confident in our choice
that we're going to grant him a decent
amount of patience.
>> Thank you guys for the opportunity. This
is an offense that's going to be built
around Lamar Jackson. Developing young
players at this current time, this
current state is one of the most
important elements of building a
successful team. Do you see yourself
calling plays on defense, Jess?
>> I do. Jesse Mentor is now the new head
coach of the Baltimore Ravens.
>> This is a home run hire for the
Baltimore Ravens.
>> I think it's great. I
>> I think it's a great hire.
>> It became apparent quickly that Jesse
Mentor was the right guy to be our next
head football coach. We really look
forward to making it we making it all of
us.
>> Ed Reed again. He's all over. It's about
winning Super Bowls. All right. It's
about creating the best team. This place
showed during the process that they
believed in me and I work every day to
prove them right that they made a great
decision.
Just been an incredible season of great
moments, unpredictable plays, and now
maybe the best rivalry the NFL has at
the moment comes down to one play to
keep alive hopes of a division title.
The Steelers bring that pressure. It's
fourth and seven. Season on the line.
JACKSON LOSSING IT UP. AND IT is
held ON TO BY ISAIAH LAKELEY AT THE 22
YD LINE. Timeout Baltimore. 12 seconds
left in field goal position.
>> Wow.
>> Oh my god. What a catch. What a catch.
I think up until that kick missed, they
still felt like they were capable of
making a Super Bowl run. So, there was
just a sense of shock and frustration
that they were unable to do it this
year. They were never able to salvage
the season. And I think people knew
there was going to be some level of
change, likely notable change in that
organization. But when I walked out of
that locker room, I just didn't know how
high the change would rise.
>> Just wasn't good enough today.
>> It's disappointing.
>> It goes on all of us. Could be a lot of
change,
>> but what you felt after that game was
palpable frustration that the season had
gotten away from them and they fell well
short of their goals. I think John
Horbaugh could have been back. I felt
like John Horabal might decide to step
away feeling like both sides could
benefit from a fresh start or I thought
it was possible that the Ravens moved
on. So Monday morning I think people
were just basically coming to grips with
the fact of wow this this season's over.
This season's been a disappointment and
obviously owner Steve Bashadi was doing
his homework, had some talks and and he
felt differently.
>> Yeah, a dramatic move for the Baltimore
Ravens. took an extra day to think about
it, but you know, this was always a
possibility. I don't know that we have
seen in a very long time as attractive
an opening as the Baltimore Ravens right
now.
>> When exactly did you make the decision
to fire John Horbal?
>> As you all know in your life, uh timing
is never right. You can't say that
timing is perfect in anything. Um, but I
but I got to the point that I didn't
believe that I would feel regret after I
made that decision. And that's what
instinct is. When you finally get to the
point that you're pretty damn sure that
you are not going to regret the decision
a day or a week later, then that's the
time to make the decision.
>> If Tyler Loop makes that field goal, is
John Harbaugh still here coaching this
team
>> for a week?
I'll say this, I got probably five or
six messages from other reporters who I
work with, not in this city, other
athletic reporters saying, "You are so
lucky that he's your owner." Wow,
Steve's an interesting guy. Anytime we
have talked uh with the Ravens owner,
Steve Bashotti, it he's always so candid
and you can ask him pretty much any
question and it comes out with no
filter. I mean, it it really is. He
shoots from the hip. I'm not doing this.
I'm not doing this to be back uh like
some of my partners doing this every
three or four years. I mean, to me,
that's that's hell on earth. We're going
to make it so right that we're going to
have a lot of patience. Is that fair to
say? We're going to be so confident in
our choice that we're going to grant him
a decent amount of patience.
>> Yeah. I mean, that was the my next
question. Okay. John Harbaugh's gone.
Who's the next coach? Who's that going
to be? Within maybe an hour of the news
of John Harbaugh being fired, I got
three texts from coaches around the
league saying Jesse Mentor is going to
be the guy.
>> Yeah. So, first of all, just just thank
you guys for the opportunity.
>> Do you see yourself calling plays on
defense, Jess?
>> I do. I do. Um, one, I think it's a
great strength of mine. Um, I think it's
it's what's put me in this position to
be sitting here speaking with you.
>> Hey, Jess, I I know you're real close to
Mike McDonald. Have you talked to him
about that first year where he became a
uh the head coach of Seattle?
>> Yeah, I've talked to him quite a bit.
Um, it's probably the only guy, you
know, from a schematic standpoint. We we
talk pretty regularly that we share some
ideas. knowing his history with the
Ravens, knowing what they value in terms
of the qualities, the emotional
intelligence, the background,
all that stuff, his knowledge of the
organization. Right from the very
beginning, you expected Jesse Mter to be
one of the top candidates. Everything is
about the the the right people and
everybody being on the same page,
everybody having the same vision.
Developing young players at this current
time, this current state is the most
important um one of the most important
elements of building a successful team.
And so, how does that happen? Right? To
me, the difference in standards and
expectations. Um I think standards are
hardcore. uh they're
they're more factual and so when you set
the standards of how things are done
versus you have expectations I think you
leave you leave some gray area within
expectations and expectations a little
bit more of like a hope and a wish uh we
hope to do this and a standard is like
man no this is this is how we're going
to do this this is how we're going to
operate
>> communication it all starts there
>> there's two different ways we're going
to do it So
>> you're either like mugged up there.
>> Yeah.
>> And you've done that in a game before.
>> So if I slide to you and you feel the
center coming to you, you're going to
pick him.
>> Stay as skinny as you can
>> definitely.
>> And then be ready to ricochet back up
field.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Like you're not you're not
going to you're not going to like it's
not going to be as forceful.
>> Yeah.
>> But it's going to be like skinny flat
flat flat. You may be the guy to sneak
through
>> cuz this center as you do this as you go
to pick him and they slide to you like
this center is going to be doing that.
Yeah,
>> you got to get skinny and use your pass
rush. Move now.
>> Yes, sir.
>> There's also a sense of look, he was
their guy from the beginning. This was
the favorite going in and I'd concede he
was one of the favorites. But I think if
you have your mind made up before the
end, you enter the process, you're not
interviewing 20 people. But he blew him
away and they didn't want to lose him.
There was other teams that were
interested in him and they just didn't
want to risk losing him. Creating a
partnership with Lamar as myself as the
head coach is the very first priority.
This is an offense that's going to be
built around Lamar Jackson. Creating an
environment where he feels like the
system is helping him become the best
player he can be. That it gives him
answers that he's learning a system of
offense and not just a collaboration of
plays. Like with myself, I think, hey,
let's let's build the best defense in
the NFL. That's a quarterback's best
friend to begin with. Feel like mentor
make a good head coach?
>> Yeah. He make whatever he want to be.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Why is that?
>> Cuz he's that guy. He that leader alpha,
man. He's not looking. He He like Alpha,
man. The guys play hard for him, man.
And I just feel like he's just that
dude, man. Every day you know what you
going to get with him.
>> Duran and and Kyle obviously they've
been they've drawn comparisons in the
past, but it's like those guys are
weapons in the same way that an
offensive weapon you would say. I don't
know that he has a position. I think
he's just a weapon, you know, and how
can we move this guy around, not let the
other side take his ability to make
plays out of the equation.
>> That dude, I mean, he has got figured
out.
>> Yeah, he's killing it.
>> I mean, I was talking to Pat and there
was one time uh in the game where it was
a big third down, I think, and um and he
he put together a blitz that we had not
seen before on on tape. and uh and got
us and got us pretty good there.
>> There's no doubt in my mind that that
that could quickly become the type of
defense that you guys are used to.
>> Jesse Mentor was so impressive that he
was getting ready to go to another head
coaching uh interview. The Ravens said,
"Hey, just hang around." He was that
impressive.
>> My eyes were bloodshot uh sleepdeprived,
but excited. You know, it's been a a
grueling two week sprint to the finish.
Um, we interviewed 20 candidates uh over
the last two weeks. A lot of hours, a
lot of information, learned a lot, a
ton. I mean, what an exciting process to
talk to all these really brilliant
people in different organizations. And
uh, you know, it's it's been a great
process, but something I don't want to
go through again for 18 years.
>> All right, David, we have a new hiring
in the National Football League. Jesse
Mter is now the new head coach of the
Baltimore Ravens. Jessie Jessie Jesse
Mter
>> has been the defensive coordinator with
the Chargers and he has experience in
Baltimore with the Ravens.
>> 5year contract to bring him back to
Baltimore where he started his NFL
coaching career in 2017.
>> I dig this choice for the Ravens. you
started hearing Jesse Mentor's name in
terms of coaching vacancies as early as
last year during the cycle.
>> We're probably going to have to uh just
enjoy Jesse Mentor while we have him. I
mean, I had a feeling he could be a he
could be a head coach next year. We'll
be competing against him.
>> I think when he left here, it was such
on good footing and I think people knew
that he was an ascending talent.
My first sort of impression of Jesse was
when he was here as a young assistant
coach and um what I've seen is
tremendous growth. He's become one of
the pre-minent, you know, defensive play
callers in the league as a coordinator.
Uh I think he does a lot with a little
at times. I think he has a great feel
for personnel. I think he's creative. I
think he's got authority to him. I think
he has a presence about him. Great
humility. uh passion for the game. I
think he understands the Ravens culture
and the DNA in this building and I think
he's the right coach for us.
>> I think it's great. I
>> I think it's a great hire.
>> I love it. I think this is a home run
hire for the Baltimore Ravens.
>> Really happy for Jess. Very deserving.
Great great coach, great person.
Obviously, he's a friend of mine.
Really, really happy for him.
>> Of all the potential first-time head
coaches that were in the cycle, the
hottest name two months ago, one month
ago,
>> they're familiar with him. somebody on
the defensive side of the ball. Young,
hot defensive mind
>> and has been just awesome at every stop.
>> Oh my gosh.
>> Thank you.
Yep.
>> Love you.
Yeah, thank you guys so much for being
here for the warm welcome. Uh my family
and I, we could not be more excited
about this opportunity. Uh but we really
look forward to making it we making it
all of us and uh making this the it's
already the greatest uh organization in
the National Football League and we just
want to take it and take it even a step
higher and so we are so lucky, blessed
uh thankful to everybody uh for us being
here and uh can't wait to get to work.
Thank you.
>> I promised you guys that we would find a
great head coach to take us to the next
level. And in the end, we determined
that Jesse Mentor was the right coach to
take us the Super Bowl. excited that
he's here. I can't wait to get to work
with him and uh it's going to be fun.
He's also going to need your help and uh
it takes a village to have the village
in this room and I'm just thrilled to be
here today with all of you.
>> It's it's about winning Super Bowls. All
right? It's about creating the best
team. The team that can be at its best
when its best is needed. I think that's
a major piece of this. My goal will be
to work every day to prove them right.
And so, it's about proving the people
that believe in you right. And this
place showed during the process that
they believed in me and I work every day
to prove them right, that they made a
great decision.
>> Let's talk about Mentor getting hired in
Baltimore. Everybody talks about his
greatness, his leadership, how good of a
defense he has.
>> Really well-rounded, energetic, smart
coach who fits Baltimore.
>> All right, we got to roll. Yep. Got it.
>> Thank you.
>> All good.
>> All good. Roll it on.
>> All right. Cool. Three, two, one. Ravens
fans, I am so excited to introduce the
new head coach of the Baltimore Ravens,
Jesse Mentor. Doing good.
>> Yep.
>> All right. Thanks for joining.
>> This is not exactly 60 minutes. We'll
keep it fun and light.
>> Sounds good.
>> Ladies and gentlemen, the man who was
selected to guide the Baltimore Ravens
through the next chapter is Jesse Mint.
Coach,
>> how you doing, coach?
>> Doing great, man. Appreciate you guys
having me on.
>> I appreciate you doing this. Been a fan
for a long time. We all have a
>> man who just makes me smile when I see
him. What's going through your mind,
>> man? Just blessed uh humble, you know,
humble to have this opportunity.
>> How does Jesse Mentor set the culture?
>> What has it been like here for the first
few hours as a head coach in the NFL?
>> Jesse.
>> Jesse Mentor.
>> Ladies and gentlemen, it's Coach Mentor.
>> That was great.
>> So, what did you when when you got
called? What
>> um was the first thing that went through
your mind? It was it was uh just surreal
>> after being here for the day. I thought
it might happen.
>> Um so I was kind of ready for it, but
like calling my wife and telling her was
>> that was probably the coolest part.
Yeah.
>> Did you FaceTime or you called?
>> I called her and then we I was like,
"All right, I'm going to FaceTime you
guys and tell the kids." And
>> so yeah,
>> that's awesome.
>> So it was cool.
>> Look at all these cool pictures. Ray,
Louis
Ed Reed.
>> Ed Reed again. He's all over.
>> He's one of the greatest Ravens of all
time. Go.
>> Touchdown.
>> Not holding. No holding.
>> Good punt. Ready.
>> How did they react when you
>> Yeah, it was awesome.
>> That's great.
>> That's great. They're so well behaved.
>> Then when I got home, they had like the
house decorated like purple and black
and That was cool.
Exciting time for us. 30 years in the
books of Ravens football history here in
Baltimore. we know we have the talent to
go out and pursue championships. Now, uh
when we set out to find our new coach,
we wanted to make sure that we're very
serious about bringing a great leader,
but also a great person to this
organization, to our locker room. Uh and
we found that in Jesse Mentor, who will
be the next Ravens head coach.
>> It became apparent quickly that Jesse
Mentor was the right guy to be our next
head football coach. takes everybody to
be successful. I look forward to
empowering our players, the coaches that
we bring in. We will create our own
standards that will allow us to reach
our ultimate goals together. We will
build a true team built on toughness,
fundamentals, team that plays together
and we will work to be the best team in
the National Football League and we will
be at our best when our best is needed.
>> Can you talk about this process and what
was it like to go through it? I guess
you interviewed almost every team. Was
it the Ravens opening that you sort of
circled at the beginning and thought
this is where I want to be if we can
work this out?
>> Yeah, great question, Jeff. When this
job opened, this became the one for me
and this was the one that I wanted. And
knowing the history, knowing the
tradition, knowing the spine of the
organization, kind of what it's built
on, uh there was no better place for me.
What stands out to me about Jesse Mentor
is how much he seems to embrace what the
Ravens organization is all about. He
said it several times, the standard.
I've been here. I know what it's all
about. However, this is also new. We're
doing this. This is a change can be
good. And I think he's handled the whole
thing with replacing John Harbaugh
really well.
>> Talking with Jesse is his strength is
going to be connecting with players.
>> Good to see you. Hey, doing good. What's
up, brother?
>> How you doing?
>> Good to see you.
>> Hey, how are you, man?
>> Damn. How you doing, bro?
>> Good to see you. And what impressed me
the most was when he was talking about
relationships, he also acknowledged it
just doesn't happen overnight. It takes
time and to build those connections with
players.
>> Relationships take time and so you don't
you don't become the head coach of the
Ravens and expect to have a a deep
relationship with anybody. Uh so those
take time. We've we've been working
towards that already. He's been able to
take teams and units and help turn them
around quickly. And when you talk to
players, well, why is it what what does
Jesse do that helps turn around things?
They talk about how he makes you believe
in the system. And he feels that if
players feel they are part of what makes
the system go, they are more invested in
the system and they believe in it. Good
right there.
>> Take to the job classroom to the field.
>> And when you have players that have that
confidence, that's where you take what
could be a very good defense or a good
team and take it to the next level.
>> On the day Jesse got out here, you were
out standing outside and you're doing a
stand up shot behind.
>> One of my favorite moments since I've
been here.
>> So Jameson, what are you hearing about
the search uh for Monkin's replacement?
Oh, is there
>> Well, actually something but I couldn't
hear.
>> I I'm just being stopped by uh this is
Raven Ravens owner, Steve Bashadi. So I
I you know I I was standing there and uh
it was just I didn't have a cameraman,
didn't have producer. So I'm standing
there looking at my camera and when I'm
doing a solo hit, I have to stay still.
I can't move because I could be out of
frame. So I'm just standing there and
it's very cold outside. So, I'm just
still waiting for my next hit. And I
hear somebody yell behind me, "Why are
you standing out there in the cold?" At
first, I did not recognize the voice
until I felt someone come up behind me
and grab me both shoulders. And I see
it's Steve.
>> Uh, this is Raven. Raven's owner, Steve
Bashi, has joined us.
>> It's cold out here.
>> What is What is he doing outside?
>> I don't That's what I said to him. I
said, "Why aren't you doing this inside
the building for him
reporter?"
>> And I I don't know why they kicked him
to the curb, so to speak, cuz we're out
here on the curb. But But hey, why
>> that's how Steve is. He's so
comfortable. Uh where he would come on
and just exchange banter and uh this was
very offscript.
>> Why did they want to know why? Why did
you hire Jesse Mentor?
>> Oh, I I didn't. Eric didn't. I approved
it. There you go.
>> Yeah, I can tell those two are going to
work really well together. It it uh he
he stood out. We got some good
candidates out there, but he stood out.
So, we're really happy with him.
>> I don't know if there's too many owners
that have kind of uh videobombed ESPN.
>> Okay, Jameson, please go indoors.
>> That is the next order of business.
>> You're red. It's time to get inside.
Hold on. I
>> appreciate it.
>> We love it. Thanks,
As far as coaching hires, what are you
looking for in those particular
positions?
>> Those searches are going really well.
I'm looking for leaders and connectors
and relationship builders and schematic
expertise. Uh but most importantly, guys
that the players believe in, that
they're willing to they're willing to
dive deep and build really real strong
relationships with the players. What
stands out to me about the coaching
staff that Jesse Mter has constructed is
the diversity, a willingness to look
everywhere. You got some familiarity
with a couple Ravens coaches staying on.
You have them bringing in a couple
coaches who have worked with Jesse
Mentor in the past.
>> Extremely excited to be back and ready
to get to work with this guy and
everybody beside me and behind me.
>> But then you have people that have no
association to Jesse Mentor.
>> My name is Eddie Faulner, coach the
running backs. I'm coming from that team
in the AFC North that's black and gold.
You know who that is. Very happy to be
here. That that experience has given me
a great perspective on what this
organization is about and I can't wait
to get to work and win some games. A lot
of young firstear head coaches, the
tendency is to hire coaches that you're
familiar with. That's not the case with
Jesse. And in talking with Jesse after
his press conference, he mentioned that
yeah, you can bring in your your buddies
and that's one way to go, but you want
to bring in people that can bring fresh
ideas. And I think that's what he was
more wanting to do than just bring in a
lot of yesmen. as we were putting
together a coaching staff. Uh it to me
it starts with relationships and guys
that can connect with people, connect
with each other on the staff, work well
together, uh work with the players, be
very collaborative in how we approach
things. And then also just a vast
variety of experience. So we have guys
that have been coaching a long time,
some younger, some older, all with
really good experience, all in my
opinion were the best person for the job
that they were hired for as we went
throughout the process. and I know
everybody's excited to be here.
>> Uh Declan Doyle, the offensive
coordinator. I'm coming from uh Chicago.
I just want to say thank you to all you
guys. Obviously, it it takes kind of a
village to uh get to the final product
that people see on Sunday. Um and you
guys all have such a
>> What stands out to me about Declan Doyle
is what you hear from people he's worked
with.
>> Declan was extremely detailed. He's he's
a tremendous football coach. He's
bright. Uh, again, I was saying earlier,
it's never on your time clock. The time
clock for these young coaches that are
good is quicker than you might think.
And so, um, I'm excited for him because
>> absolutely.
>> Declan Doyle taking the job with
Baltimore. What do you think of that?
And what does that loss mean for you
guys?
>> It's obviously a big loss for us. Losing
Declan was definitely a very valuable
piece to us offensively.
>> Declan's a phenomenal football coach. I
mean, the guy is seasoned beyond his
years. This this has been his calling.
He's he's known for a long time that he
was going to be a football coach and
he's prepared himself accordingly. Um,
very detail oriented, has a great way to
communicating. He's very clear. So, I
think those guys are getting someone
really really good. You know, I I'm
disappointed that that we lost them as
as quickly as we did. I was hoping that
we'd be able to hold on to him for
longer.
first thing that kind of stands out is
is his age because you look up and you
want to look at different things about
him and you see 29 years old and you're
like I think Lamar Jackson is the same
age. I mean that's quite different. He's
a guy that everybody has said is wise
beyond his years. I think he has a
confidence about him. I think he has
sort of a a a swagger about him in a lot
of ways. If you watch how he answers
questions, he speaks very confidently in
what he's doing. He could have had other
jobs. He could have stayed. He had a
very good job. But this opportunity was
enough to get him to leave Chicago. And
I think that's very telling for what the
Ravens have to offer.
From a fan perspective, I've really
sensed a new energy, a belief in what
they're doing and the transparency
they've shown and the moves they made
and excitement about what is to come. I
think everyone's excited. This is going
to be a very important off season. The
coaching staff is in place, but now they
have to figure out plugging the holes on
the roster and proving as a team. But I
definitely sense renewed energy and
excitement among the fans.
>> And the new look AFC North continued in
Baltimore.
>> Main thing for me is just getting the
right people in here. So we certainly
trust Eric to build a great team.
>> Trey Hendrickson, he now lands with the
Baltimore Ravens. I'm fired up.
>> Let's go. I'm excited.
>> I'm excited. I'm
>> excited, too.
>> We're hoping to make that next step. I'm
excited to be a part of that.
>> This is a topheavy roster with elite
talent.